{"tossups": [{"question": "This country\u2019s classical music includes a suite with movements about the 1710 Siege of Viborg. This country\u2019s national anthem, \u201cMaamme,\u201d [mahhm-may] ends that collection, the<em> Karelia Suite</em>, which was written by this country\u2019s most prominent composer, Jean Sibelius. Sibelius\u2019 most famous work is named for this country and protested Russian censorship of its early 20th century nationalism. For ten points, name this country where many of Sibelius\u2019 works were premiered in Helsinki.", "answer": "<b> Finland</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "In this country, Erich Hoenmanns sparked the Mechelen Incident after he crashed his plane, revealing a planned invasion called Case Yellow. This country was the target of the 18 Days\u201d Campaign, which included a valiant but futile defense at the river Leie. The Force Publique, soldiers from this country\u2019s colony the Congo, clashed with Italian soldiers in World War II. Leopold III led, for ten points, what country that surrendered to Germany after the fall of Brussels?", "answer": "<b> Belgium</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this conflict, suspected collaborators were tortured in the Phoenix Program. The Siege of Khe Sanh took place in this conflict after it was widened following a phantom attack on the USS<em> Maddox</em> in the Gulf of Tonkin. American troops in this conflict were criticized for their use of Agent Orange. For ten points, name this unpopular Southeast Asian war that ended with the capture of Saigon.", "answer": "<b> Vietnam</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A race riot in this state destroyed the neighborhood of Greenwood, which was known as \u201cBlack Wall Street.\u201d The Red River of the South is the southern border of this state, whose capital was the target of the Timothy McVeigh bombing. The Trail of Tears took Native Americans to this state, which was then called \u201cIndian Territory.\u201d The \u201cSooners\u201d settled, for ten points, what state directly north of Texas?", "answer": "<b> Oklahoma</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s premier was nearly blown up by a bomb on the<em> Kashmir Princess</em> while dispatched to the Bandung Conference. The Cultural Revolution was organized by this man to stop bourgeois infiltrators from restoring capitalism in his country. This man first came to prominence while leading the Long March to save his army from the Nationalists.<em> The Little Red Book</em> is a collection of sayings by, for ten points, what father of Communist China?", "answer": "<b> Mao</b> Zedong", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "24,000 tons of dynamite were detonated at once so that this project could utilize the Culebra Cut. This project, which was greatly expanded after a 2006 referendum approved the Third Lock project, was the subject of the Torrijos-Carter treaties. Theodore Roosevelt supported the construction of, for ten points, what Central American waterway that connects the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans?", "answer": "<b> Panama Canal</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man expressed his desire that \u201cpoisonous envenomed worms\u201d be drafted into forced labor, and demanded synagogues be burned to the ground in his<em> On the Jews and their Lies</em>. Frederick III kidnapped this man and held him in Wartburg Castle to protect him from the Holy Roman Emperor. In<em> Exsurge</em> <em>Domine</em>, Leo X threatened this man with excommunication if he didn\u2019t recant his beliefs. For ten points, name this former German friar who created the<em> 95 Theses</em>.", "answer": "Martin<b> Luther</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "John Singer Sargent created a portrait of this man \u201cpainting by the edge of a wood\u201d with his wife Alice. This artist, who observed and painted the Rouen Cathedral under several different light conditions, built a garden-filled estate in Giverny [zhi-vair-nee] that is now a museum dedicated to him. Japanese-style bridges and water lilies were popular subjects of paintings by, for ten points, what French painter whose painting of a sunrise gave its name to the Impressionist movement?", "answer": "Claude<b> Monet</b> [moh-nay]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In the aftermath of this battle, Benjamin Lincoln accepted the sword of Charles O\u2019Hara. The losing side in this battle attempted to retreat to Gloucester Point. A British band at this battle may have started playing \u201cThe World Turned Upside Down.\u201d A fleet under Comte de Rochambeau blocked reinforcements from this battle in the Battle of Chesapeake Bay. Charles Cornwallis was defeated at, for ten points, what 1781 battle, the final major clash of the American Revolution?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Yorktown</b> <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An obscene message opposing this policy was protected as free speech in<em> Cohen v. California</em>. In 1863, working-class men, resentful of wealthy people\u2019s ability to pay a $300 fee to be exempt from this policy, started a riot in New York City. During the Vietnam War, this process was carried out by televised lottery. For ten points, name this policy of mandatory military service.", "answer": "<b> conscription</b> (accept the<b> draft</b> ; accept<b> Selective Service</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man executed thousands of prisoners after launching the Night Attack on Targovishite. Matthias Corvinus imprisoned this man after he asked for help against Mehmed II. This man was engaged in a power struggle with Vladislav II, who was backed by John Hunyadi. This man became Voivode of Wallachia after the death of his father. For ten points, name this Romanian ruler named for his habit of putting his enemies on stakes.", "answer": "<b> Vlad III</b> Dracul (accept<b> Vlad the Imapler</b>; prompt on \u201cVlad\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 1636, conflict over control of this resource in the Connecticut River Valley led to the Pequot War. French-Canadian traders, known as<em> Coureurs des bois</em>, traveled the woods exchanging European goods for this resource. In the early 19th century, John Jacob Astor founded a company dealing in this commodity to counter the Hudson\u2019s Bay Company\u2019s monopoly. For ten points, name this commodity often acquired from beaver pelts.", "answer": "<b> fur</b> (accept<b> pelt</b>s before it is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Martin Klaproth discovered this element in pitchblende, which can be processed into yellowcake. This element, which alpha decays into thorium, is most commonly found in a 238 isotope, and its 235 isotope is enriched for nuclear fuel. For ten points, name this radioactive element named for the seventh planet from the sun, with symbol U.", "answer": "<b> uranium</b> (accept<b> U</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A president of this nation, Abdal\u00b4a Bucaram, was once an Olympic-caliber hurdler and became known as \u201cEl Loco\u201d during his tenure. This nation\u2019s most recent election brought</b> <b>the wheelchair-bound Lenin (+)</b> <b>Moreno to power, succeeding his mentor Rafael Correa.</b> <b>Moreno allowed Scotland Yard to enter this nation\u2019s (*)</b> embassy in London in 2019 to arrest the founder of WikiLeaks. For ten points, name this country that protected Julian Assange and has capital Quito.", "answer": "<b> Ecuador</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The entrance of one of these structures was graffitied in honor of Frederick Wilhelm IV</b> <b>by Karl Lepsius, who composed a list of these structures after visiting (+)</b> <b>Dahshur. One</b> <b>of these structures, carved from white limestome and featuring six mastabas stacked upon each other, was designed for (*)</b> Djoser by Imhotep. Despite their common use as tombs, there are none of these structures in the Valley of the Kings. Khufu, Menkaure, and Khafre commissioned, for ten points, what common tomb for Pharaohs, three of which are at Giza?", "answer": "<b> pyramid</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {}, {"question": "Multiple members of this team, including Buck Weaver and Shoeless Joe Jackson, were (*)</b> accused of taking bribes to throw the 1919 World Series, after which it took until 2005 to win another World Series. For ten points, name this baseball team that experienced the \u201cBlack Sox\u201d scandal.", "answer": "Chicago<b> White Sox</b> (prompt on \u201cChicago\u201d; prompt on \u201cSox\u201d)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Alexandre Gonsse de Rougeville attempted to save this monarch in the Carnation Plot. This royal\u2019s signature was forged in an attempt to sell expensive jewelry in the (+) Affair of the Diamond Necklace. The Petit Trianon, originally designed for Madame de Pompadour, was given to this woman. This woman was forced to flee to (*)</b> Tuileries Palace under the watch of the Marquis de Lafayette after a crowd seized Versailles. For ten points, name this wife of Louis XVI who legendarily said \u201cLet them eat cake\u201d during the French Revolution.", "answer": "<b> Marie Antoinette</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>A leader of this country, Egon Krenz, was sentenced to 6 years in prison for</b> <b>allowing troops to fire on civilians. The Hallstein Doctrine targeted countries that</b> <b>recognized this state. This country adopted a policy of (+)</b> <b>\u201cconsumer socialism\u201d</b> <b>under the rule of Erich Honecker. Under Walter (*)</b> Ulbricht, this country\u2019s secret police, the Stasi, committed many atrocities. For ten points, name this Communist-state that reunited with its western neighbor after the fall of the Berlin Wall. ANSWER:<b> East Germany</b> (accept<b> German Democratic Republic</b>; do not prompt on Germany alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}